Guide to the North Cascades Audubon Society Records 1967-2017
Western Washington University, Center for Pacific Northwest Studies
North Cascades Audubon Society Records
1967-2017
XOE_CPNWS0334ncas
Center for Pacific Northwest Studies Goltz-Murray Building 808 25th St Bellingham, WA, 98225-9123 360 650 7534 cpnws@wwu.edu
6.0 linear feet 9 boxes
The North Cascades Audubon Society (NCAS) Records documents environmental interests and activities of a non-profit group based in Whatcom County, Washington.
North Cascades Audubon Society.
Collection is organized in accordance with the following series (and subseries) arrangement:
Series I: Administrative Records
Series II: Financial Records
Series III: Published Materials
Sub-Series I: Avalanche
Sub-Series II: Other Publications
Series IV: Christmas Bird Counts
Series V: Awards
Biographical/Historical note
The North Cascades Audubon Society (NCAS) was founded in 1970 in Whatcom County, Washington, as the local branch of the National Audubon Society. The organization is dedicated to protecting and promoting awareness of wildlife, habitat and environment. NCAS is heavily involved in environmental advocacy through scientific research, environmental education, conservation and stewardship activities. In additon to their advocacy and educational work, the organization publishes 'The Avalanche,' a newletter discussing natural history and local environmental issues.
The North Cascades Audubon Society (NCAS) Records document the activities and interests of the Whatcom County, Washington branch of the National Audubon Society. The collection reflects the group's work to protect and promote awareness of the importance of wildlife, habitat and the environment in Whatcom county since its founding in 1970. The collection spans from 1970 to 2014, and includes meeting minutes, correspondence, membership information, budget information, and published materials, specifically the monthly newsletter Avalanche.
Administrative records are dated from 1975 to 2017 and include Board of Director’s meeting agendas and minutes, chapter and membership information and correspondence between the NCAS and other environmental groups. Financial records are dated from 1984 to 2017 and include account books and ledgers, budget reports, profit versus loss analyses and financial based correspondence with the National branch. Published materials are dated from 1970 to 2017 and include one brochure about the NCAS as well as every issue of the monthly newletter Avalanche, created by the NCAS. Christmas Bird Count resources document NCAS's annual efforts to collect data about the presence of various species in the area, dating from 1967 to 2008.
The George and Lois Garlick family papers at CPNWS include correspondence and Avalanche newsletters from the North Cascades Audubon Society.
Collection is open to the public.
Original set of records donated by the North Cascades Audubon Society in February 2014. Additional "Christmas Bird Count" materials were transferred by Milt Krieger on behalf of Judy Krieger in July 2018.
North Cascades Audubon Society.; Environmentalism--Washington (State)--Whatcom County--History--Sources.; Whatcom County (Wash.)--History--Sources.; Environmental Activism
- Administrative Records, 1975-2017; Series I
  - Minutes CD, 2011-2013 (Box-folder 1/1)
  - Board of Directors Agenda/Minutes, 1997-2002 (Box-folder 1/2)
  - Board of Directors Agenda/Minutes, 2002-2005 (Box-folder 1/3)
  - Board of Directors Agenda/Minutes, 2005 (Box-folder 1/4)
  - Board of Directors Agenda/Minutes, 2005-2011 (Box-folder 1/5)
  - Board of Directors Agenda/Minutes, 2006-2011 (Box-folder 1/6)
  - Board of Directors Agenda/Minutes, 2011-2014 (Box-folder 1/7)
  - Board of Directors Agenda/Minutes, 2015-2017 (Box-folder 1/8)
  - Constitution & Bylaws, 1982-1999 (Box-folder 1/9)
  - Audubon Correspondence, 1975-2004 (Box-folder 1/10)
  - Letters to Linda Wendler, in charge of Chapter mailing list, 1987-1991 (Box-folder 1/11)
  - Letters to Trina, in charge of Chapter mailing list, 1991-2000 (Box-folder 1/12)
  - NCAS correspondences, 2016 (Box-folder 1/13)
  - Audubon-Washington Leadership Conference, 2001 (Box-folder 1/14)
  - Annual Chapter Certification Report, 1995-2003 (Box-folder 1/15)
  - Annual Report Form, 2000-2007 (Box-folder 1/16)
  - Chapter Leader Change Report Form, 2000-2006 (Box-folder 1/17)
  - Chapter Change Report, 1985-1989 (Box-folder 1/18)
  - Chapter Change Report, 1989-1991 (Box-folder 1/19)
  - Chapter Change Report, 1992-1994 (Box-folder 1/20)
  - Chapter Change Report, 1995-1997 (Box-folder 1/21)
  - Chapter Change Report, 1998-2000 (Box-folder 1/22)
  - Chapter Change Report, 1999-2000 (Box-folder 1/23)
  - NCAS Membership Meetings & Special Events, 1970-1998 (Box-folder 1/24)
  - Membership Committee Guide, 1998 (Box-folder 1/25)
  - Audubon Annual Membership List, 1985-1992 (Box-folder 1/26)
  - Audubon Annual Membership List, 1993-1998 (Box-folder 1/27)
  - NCAS Membership Statistics, 1993-2000 (Box-folder 1/28)
  - "Chapters and the 2020 Vision", 2001 (Box-folder 1/29)
  - Whatcom Land Trust Quit Claim Deed (Box-folder 1/30)
- Financial Records, 1979-2017; Series II
  - Account Book, 1979-1984 (Box-folder 2/1)
  - Account Book, 1985-1987 (Box-folder 2/2)
  - Account Book, 1988-1989 (Box-folder 2/3)
  - Account Book, 1990 (Box-folder 2/4)
  - Treasuer Reports, 2008-2010 (Box-folder 2/5)
  - Net Worth Report, 1995 (Box-folder 2/6)
  - National Audubon Society Correspondence re: Membership Due and Payment Incentives, 1994-2004 (Box-folder 2/7)
  - Budget Information, 1984-1990 (Box-folder 2/8)
  - Budget Information, 1991 (Box-folder 2/9)
  - Budget Information, 1992 (Box-folder 2/10)
  - Budget Information, 1993-1995 (Box-folder 2/11)
  - Budget Information, 1996-1997 (Box-folder 2/12)
  - Budget Information, 1998 (Box-folder 2/13)
  - Budget Information, 1999-2001 (Box-folder 2/14)
  - Budget Information, 2002-2004 (Box-folder 2/15)
  - Budget Information, 2005-2006 (Box-folder 2/16)
  - Budget Information, 2007-2008 (Box-folder 2/17)
  - Budget Information, 2016-2017 (Box-folder 2/18)
  - Electronic Information (CD-ROM): Quickbook backup file, Excel Budgets, and Misc. Membership, 2001-2008 (Box-folder 2/19)
- Published Materials, 1970-2017; Series III
  - Avalanche, 1970-2017; Sub-Series I
    - North Cascades Audubon Society Photocopy Originals for Avalanche Subscribers, undated (Box-folder 2/20)
    - Avalanche Subscribers, 1999-2001 (Box-folder 2/21)
    - NCAS Archives (Box-folder 2/22)
    - Christmas bird count, 1972, 1976-1978, 1981 (Box-folder 2/23)
    - Avalanche, 1970-1977 (Box-folder 2/24)
    - Avalanche, 1978-1983 (Box-folder 2/25)
    - Avalanche, 1984-1985 (Box-folder 2/26)
    - Avalanche, 1986-1987 (Box-folder 2/27)
    - Avalanche, 1988-1989 (Box-folder 2/28)
    - Avalanche, 1990-1991 (Box-folder 2/29)
    - Avalanche, 1992-1993 (Box-folder 2/30)
    - Avalanche, 1994-1995 (Box-folder 2/31)
    - Avalanche, 1996-1997 (Box-folder 2/32)
    - Avalanche, 1998-1999 (Box-folder 2/33)
    - Avalanche, 2000-2002 (Box-folder 2/34)
    - Avalanche, 2003-2005 (Box-folder 2/35)
    - Avalanche, 2006-2008 (Box-folder 2/36)
    - Avalanche, 2009-2011 (Box-folder 2/37)
    - Avalanche, 2012-2013 (Box-folder 2/38)
    - Avalanche, 2014-2015 (Box-folder 2/39)
    - Avalanche, 2016-2017 (Box-folder 2/40)
  - Other Publications, undated; Sub-Series II
    - North Cascades Audubon Society Brochure, undated (Box-folder 2/41)
    - Press, 2014-2016 (Box-folder 2/42)
    - Wings Over Water Article & Brochure, 2016 (Box-folder 2/43)
    - Whatcom Museum fact Sheets, Undated (Box-folder 2/44)
- Activities, 1967-2008; Series IV
  - Christmas Bird Counts, 1967-2008; Sub-Series I
    According to the North Cascades Audubon Society’s (NCAS) website (accessed here on July 24, 2018: https://www.northcascadesaudubon.org/birding/christmas-bird-count/), the annual Christmas bird counts (CBCs) “…began in 1900 as an alternative to the traditional Christmas ‘side hunt,’ where the objective was to KILL as many birds as you could. Ornithologist Frank Chapman called for an end to this slaughter by suggesting that, rather than shooting birds, people count them instead.” NCAS sponsors two local Christmas bird counts: “Bellingham” and “Washington State Ferry” (formerly called “San Juan Ferry”). The following sub-series contains instructions, forms and membership lists for, and correspondence about the local Christmas bird counts, organized chronologically by year and by area.
    - Christmas Bird Count (CBC) forms, undated (Box-folder 3/1)
    - CBC area/territory maps, undated (Box-folder 3/2)
    - CBC - Bellingham, 1967-1971 (Box-folder 3/3-3/7)
    - CBC - Bellingham, 1972-1977 (Box-folder 4/1-4/6)
    - CBC - Bellingham, 1978-1983 (Box-folder 5/1-5/6)
    - CBC - Bellingham, 1984-1990 (Box-folder 6/1-6/7)
    - CBC - Bellingham, 1991-1997 (Box-folder 7/1-7/7)
    - CBC - Bellingham, 1998-2008 (Box-folder 8/1-8/11)
    - CBC - Padilla Bay, 1979-1980; 1985-1995 (Box-folder 8/12)
    - CBC - San Juan Ferry/San Juan Islands maps, undated (Box-folder 8/13)
    - CBC - San Juan Ferry/San Juan Islands, 1982-1983; 1993-1995; 1997-1998 (Box-folder 8/14)
    - CBC - San Juan Ferry/San Juan Islands, 2000; 2002; 2004; 2006 (Box-folder 8/15)
- Awards, 1972-1991; Series V
  - NCAS Appreciation Plaque, May 1991 (Box-folder 9/1)
  - National Audubon Society Chapter Charter to NCAS, 1972 (Box-folder 9/2)